Guide to the Frederic Prokosch Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederic Prokosch collection
1908-1968
1935-1952
YCAL MSS 685
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.17
(14 boxes)
The Frederic Prokosch collection contains material by or relating to American novelist and translator Frederic Prokosch. There are corrected drafts and proofs to several early novels, including The Asiatics (1935), The Seven Who Fled (1937), The Conspirators (1943), Age of Thunder (1945), The Idols of the Cave (1946), and Storm and Echo (1948). There are also drafts of shorter works, including stories and individual poems, as well as three collections of poetry dating from the same period, specifically, The Assassions (1936), The Carnival (1938), and Death at Sea (1940). Additional materials include correspondence, photographs, printed material, such as clippings and reviews, and personal and family papers.
Prokosch, Frederic, 1908-1989
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, 1941-1999. For additional information see the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available for portions of the collection.
Frederic Prokosch (1908-1989)
Frederic Prokosch, novelist and translator, was born May 17, 1908, in Madison, Wisconsin, to Edouard and Mathilde (Dapprich) Prokosch. He was educated at Haverford College (1926, 1928), the University of Pennsylvania, Yale University (1933), and Cambridge University. Prokosch served as an instructor in English at Yale University (1932-1934), a faculty member at New York University (1936-1937), and a cultural attache for the U.S. Office of War Information in Stockholm (1943-1944) before spending most of the rest of his life in Europe. His first novel, The Asiastics (1935), a picaresque novel about a young man's travels from Lebanon to China, drew praise from established literary figures, and his second novel, The Seven Who Fled (1937), earned the Harper Prize. Prokosch's memoir, Voices, appeared in 1984. He died June 2, 1989, in Plan de Grasse, France.
Biographical information taken from "Frederic Prokosch." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2003. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 4 Jan. 2013.
Scope and Contents
The Frederic Prokosch collection contains material by or relating to American novelist and translator Frederic Prokosch. There are corrected drafts and proofs to several early novels, including The Asiatics (1935), The Seven Who Fled (1937), The Conspirators (1943), Age of Thunder (1945), The Idols of the Cave (1946), and Storm and Echo (1948). There are also drafts of shorter works, including stories and individual poems, as well as three collections of poetry dating from the same period, specifically, The Assassions (1936), The Carnival (1938), and Death at Sea (1940). Additional materials include correspondence, photographs, printed material, such as clippings and reviews, and personal and family papers.
Arrangement
Organized into ten groupings by date of acquisition: I. August 1941 Acquisition. II November 1941 Acquisition. III October 1944 Acquisition. IV. 1945-1948 Acquisitions. V. March 1963 Acquisition. VI. October 1963 Acquisition. VII. July 1992 Acquisition. VIII. November 1993 Acquisition. IX. December 1999 Acquisition. X. Other Acquisitions.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Prokosch, Frederic, 1908-1989
- I. August 1941 Acquisition, [1935?]-undated; 4
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  The August 1941 Acquisition consists of drafts of three manuscripts, including Prokosch's first published novel, The Asiatics (1935).
  Former call number: Za Prokosch.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of William Ruff.
  - The Asiatics, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, [circa 1935]; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Elizabeth Island," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1)
  - Untitled autograph manuscript (incomplete), corrected, undated (Box 1)
- II. November 1941 Acquisition, 1929-1933; 0.42; (1 box)
  The November 1941 Acquisition consists of shorter writings by Prokosch, including stories and collections of poems.
  - "Cupid's Whirligig" and "Hecate's House," typescript, 1930 (Box 1)
  - "Death In Autumn," poems, typescript, 1929 (Box 1)
  - "Death of a Poet," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Flamingoes," poems, typescript, 1933 (Box 2)
  - "Fog Over the Wisconsin," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "Idyll in Bavaria," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Lagoon," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Lonely Unicorn," poems, typescript, 1929 (Box 2)
  - "A Love Story," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "Mexican Nosegay," story, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "My Friend Waldemar," story, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "Old Fortunatus," poems, typescript carbon, corrected, 1931 (Box 2)
  - "A Passenger to Asia," poems, typescript, 1931 (Box 2)
  - "Peninsula Evening," story, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Promenade," story, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Return From the Picnic," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Somnabulists," poems, typescript carbon, and "The Wolves," poems, typescript, 1933 (Box 2)
  - "The Statue In the Garden," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Stranger," typescript, 1931 (Box 3)
  - "Thief, Thief!" autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - "View of Lisbon," story, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - "Visit To the Margravine," autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - Untitled autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
- III. October 1944 Acquisition, [circa 1935]-1942; 0.64; (2 boxes)
  The October 1944 Acquisition consists of corrected drafts and proofs for the three novels The Asiatics (1935), The Conspirators (1943), and The Seven Who Fled (1937).
  Gift of Mrs. Edward Prokosch.
  - The Asiatics, typescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, [circa 1935]; 2 (Box 3)
  - The Conspirators, typescript carbon, corrected, with printer's annotations, undated (Box 3)
  - The Conspirators, page proof, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1942 (Box 3)
  - The Conspirators, page proof, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1942 November (Box 4)
  - The Seven Who Fled, typescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, [circa 1937]; 2 (Box 4)
- IV. 1945-1948 Acquisitions, 0.42; (1 box)
  The 1945-1948 Acquisitions include drafts of the novels Age of Thunder (1945), The Idols of the Cave (1946), and Storm and Echo (1948).
  Gift of Frederic Prokosch.
  - Age of Thunder, draft, typescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Age of Thunder, draft, typescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1945 (Box 5)
  - The Idols of the Cave, draft, typescript and autograph manuscript, corrected, [circa 1946]; 2 (Box 5)
  - Storm and Echo, draft, typescript, corrected, 1948 (Box 5)
- V. March 1963 Acquisition, 1935-1952; 0.42; (1 box)
  The March 1963 Acquisition consists of corrected galley and plate proofs of the novel The Seven Who Fled (1937) and a publisher's correspondence file relating to Prokosch.
  Gift of Harper & Brothers.
  - The Seven Who Fled, galley proof, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1937 (Box 6)
  - The Seven Who Fled, plate proof, corrected, with proofreaders' marks and printer's annotations, 1937 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1952, undated (Box 6)
- VI. October 1963 Acquisition, [circa 1964]; 0.42; (1 box)
  The October 1963 Acquisition consists of a typescript mimeograph draft of The Dark Dancer (1964).
  Gift of The Book of the Month Club.
  - The Dark Dancer, draft, typescript mimoegraph, [circa 1964] (Box 7)
- VII. July 1992 Acquisition, 1935-1940; 0.42; (1 box)
  The July 1992 Acquisition consists of material relating to the novel The Asiatics (1935) and three collections of poems, The Assassions (1936), The Carnival (1938), and Death at Sea (1940). Materials include manuscript notes and draft fragments, correspondence, and printed ephemera.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS 288.
  Purchased from Bertram Rota on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund.
  - The Asiatics, correspondence, 1935, undated (Box 8)
  - The Assassins, draft, proofs, printed material, and correspondence, 1936, undated; 6 (Box 8)
  - The Carnival, proofs, printed material, and correspondence, 1938, undated; 11 (Box 8)
  - Death at Sea, drafts and correspondence, 1940, undated; 5 (Box 8)
- VIII. November 1993 Acquisition, 1935-1959; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  The November 1993 Acquisition consists of manuscript drafts and fragments of poems removed from printed material.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS 388.
  Gift of Jack H. Bady.
  - "Among the Caves", undated (Box 9)
  - [Andromeda], 1938 October 11 (Box 9)
  - "The Assassins", 1935 November 2 (Box 9)
  - "Banquet Song", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Death Ship", 1958, undated (Box 9)
  - "The Dolls", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Enemies", undated (Box 9)
  - "Fable", undated (Box 9)
  - "Fire Song", [1955?] November 12 (Box 9)
  - "The Flamingoes", 1948, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "The Ghost City", 1959, undated (Box 9)
  - "Going Southward", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Grotto", undated (Box 9)
  - "Island Song", undated (Box 9)
  - "Jungle Song", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Mirror", undated (Box 9)
  - "Phantom Song", undated (Box 9)
  - [The Red Sea], undated (Box 9)
  - "The Sacred Wood", undated (Box 9)
  - "Snow Song", 1949; 2 (Box 9)
  - "Song", 1941, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - "Sunburned Ulysses", 1941 July (Box 9)
  - "The Survivors", undated (Box 9)
  - "Temple Song", 1954 (Box 9)
  - [Three Deaths], undated (Box 9)
  - [Three Images], undated (Box 9)
  - [Three Mysteries], undated (Box 9)
  - [Three Sorrows], undated (Box 9)
  - "The Voyage", 1933 July 12 (Box 9)
  - "Wood Song", 1951[December] (Box 9)
  - Works by others, undated; 5 (Box 9)
    Contains proofs for limited editions prepared by Prokosch
  - Works by others, undated; 2 (Box 10)
- IX. December 1999 Acquisition, 1908-1968; 3; (3 boxes)
  The December 1999 Acquisition consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, printed material, and family papers by or relating to Frederic Prokosch and the Prokosh family.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 16.
  Gift of the Prokosch family.
  - Inventory, undated (Box 11)
  - Photographs, [1937-1943] (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1943 (Box 11)
  - Poetry: A Magazine of Verse, 1940 (Box 11)
  - Assorted journalism and review articles, 1936-1968 (Box 11)
  - Haverford College Record, 1925 (Box 11)
  - The Criterion, 1934 (Box 11)
  - Warning to a Traveller, undated (Box 11)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 11)
  - Silhouetter, undated (Box 11)
  - Notebook, Biology 2, undated (Box 11)
  - Siegfried's Sage, In Bildern, undated (Box 11)
  - A Sunset After a Storm, [1920] (Box 11)
  - Short stories, undated (Box 11)
  - The Haverfordian, 1924 (Box 11)
  - The Assassins, undated (Box 11)
  - Passport, 1935 (Box 11)
  - The Enemies, The Mirror, 1934-1960 (Box 11)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Key, undated (Box 11)
  - Childhood drawings, undated (Box 11)
  - Drawings and water colors, undated (Box 11)
  - Art notes, undated (Box 11)
  - Educational documents, 1909-1917 (Box 11)
  - Marchen Buch, undated (Box 11)
  - Telephone book, undated (Box 11)
  - Maerchen Charaktere, undated (Box 11)
  - YMCA, American Kennel Club, 1908-1930 (Box 11)
  - The Carnival, undated (Box 11)
  - Nine Days to Mukalla, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings and articles, 1936-1938 (Box 11)
  - Reviews of The Assassins, 1936 (Box 11)
  - Reviews and clippings for The Carnival, 1936-1940 (Box 11)
  - Reviews of The Night of the Poor, 1939 (Box 11)
  - Reviews and clippings for The Asiatics, 1936-1941 (Box 11)
  - The English Novel, edited by Verschoyle, 1936 (Box 11)
  - Moult Anthology, 1936-1940 (Box 11)
  - The Skies of Europe, 1941-1944 (Box 11)
  - Age of Thunder, 1945 (Box 11)
  - Voices: A Memoir, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Death at Sea, 1941 (Box 11)
  - The Seven Who Fled, 1937-1943 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1921-1943; 2 (Box 12)
  - Storm and Echo, 1948 (Box 12)
  - The Conspirators, 1943; 2 (Box 12)
  - The Skies of Europe, 1941-1943 (Box 12)
  - Reviews of The Asiatics, 1935-1936 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1939; 10 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1951, undated; 17 (Box 13)
- X. Other Acquisitions, 1933-undated; 2
  Arranged chronologically by acquisition.
  This grouping contains other small acquisitions of material by or relating to Frederic Prokosch.
  Acquired by gift from various sources. For additional information see the appropriate curator.
  - "Moliere," poem, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 14)
  - "The Centaur," poems, typescript carbon, 1933 (Box 14)